<!-- This is not xml actually, but it looks and behaves like it.
     Including an xml library would need too much resources.
     Tips between the platform specific tags are shown only on those platforms.
     Do not escape characters or use the CDATA tag. -->
<tips>
    <tip>Simply pick the same color as a friend to play together as a clan. Each of you will still control his or her own hedgehogs but they’ll win or lose together.</tip>
    <tip>Some weapons might do only low damage but they can be a lot more devastating in the right situation. Try to use the Desert Eagle to knock multiple hedgehogs into the water.</tip>
    <tip>If you’re unsure what to do and don’t want to waste ammo, skip one round. But don’t let too much time pass as there will be Sudden Death!</tip>
    <tip>Want to save ropes? Release the rope in mid air and then shoot again. As long as you don’t touch the ground or miss a shot you’ll reuse your rope without wasting ammo!</tip>
    <tip>If you’d like to keep others from using your preferred nickname on the official server, register an account at <a href="https://www.hedgewars.org/">https://www.hedgewars.org/</a>.</tip>
    <tip>You're bored of default gameplay? Try one of the missions—they'll offer different gameplay depending on the one you picked.</tip>
    <tip>By default the game will always record the last game played as a demo. Select “Local Game” and pick the “Demos” button on the lower right corner to play or manage them.</tip>
    <tip>Hedgewars is free software (Open Source) we create in our spare time. If you’ve got problems, ask on our forums or visit our IRC room!</tip>
    <tip>Hedgewars is free software (Open Source) we create in our spare time. If you like it, feel free to help us with a small donation or contribute your own work!</tip>
    <tip>Hedgewars is free software (Open Source) we create in our spare time. Share it with your family and friends as you like!</tip>
    <tip>Hedgewars is free software (Open Source) we create in our spare time, just for fun! Meet the developers in <a href="irc://irc.freenode.net/hedgewars">#hedgewars</a>!</tip>
    <tip>From time to time there will be official tournaments. Upcoming events will be announced at <a href="https://www.hedgewars.org/">https://www.hedgewars.org/</a> some days in advance.</tip>
    <tip>Hedgewars is available in many languages. If the translation in your language seems to be missing or outdated, feel free to contact us!</tip>
    <tip>Hedgewars can be run on lots of different operating systems including Microsoft Windows, macOS and GNU/Linux.</tip>
    <tip>Always remember you’re able to set up your own games in local and network/online play. You’re not restricted to the “Simple Game” option.</tip>
    <tip>Connect one or more gamepads before starting the game to be able to assign their controls to your teams.</tip>
    <tip>Consider giving yourself a short break at least once an hour to guard against strain from playing.</tip>
    <tip>If your graphics card isn’t able to provide hardware-accelerated OpenGL, try to enable the low quality mode to improve performance.</tip>
    <tip>If your graphics card isn’t able to provide hardware-accelerated OpenGL, try to update the associated drivers.</tip>
    <tip>We’re open to suggestions and constructive feedback. If you don’t like something or got a great idea, let us know!</tip>
    <tip>For your own benefit we'd like you to be polite and friendly while playing on our server. Also please keep in mind that some players are minors!</tip>
    <tip>Special game modes such as “Vampirism” or “Karma” allow you to develop completely new tactics. Try them in a custom game!</tip>
    <tip>Please don't install Hedgewars on computers you don’t own (school, university, work, etc.) unless you got permission. We don't want you to get into any trouble.</tip>
    <tip>Hedgewars can be perfect for short games during breaks. Just ensure you don’t add too many hedgehogs or use an huge map. Reducing time and health might help as well.</tip>
    <tip>No hedgehogs were harmed in making this game.</tip>
    <tip>There are three different jumps available. Tap [high jump] twice to do a very high/backwards jump.</tip>
    <tip>Afraid of falling off a cliff? Hold down [precise] to turn [left] or [right] without actually moving.</tip>
    <tip>Some weapons require special strategies or just lots of training, so don’t give up on a particular tool if you miss an enemy once.</tip>
    <tip>Most weapons won’t work once they touch the water. The Homing Bee as well as the Cake are exceptions to this.</tip>
    <tip>The Old Limburger only causes a small explosion. However the wind affected smelly cloud can poison lots of hogs at once.</tip>
    <tip>The Piano Strike is the most damaging air strike. You’ll lose the hedgehog performing it, so there’s a huge downside as well.</tip>
    <tip>The Homing Bee can be tricky to use. Its turn radius depends on its velocity, so try to not use full power.</tip>
    <tip>Sticky Mines are a perfect tool to create small chain reactions knocking enemy hedgehogs into dire situations … or water.</tip>
    <tip>The Hammer is most effective when used on bridges or girders. Hit hogs will just break through the ground.</tip>
    <tip>If you’re stuck behind an enemy hedgehog, use the Hammer to free yourself without getting damaged by an explosion.</tip>
    <tip>The Cake’s maximum walking distance depends on the ground it has to pass. Use [attack] to detonate it early.</tip>
    <tip>The Flamethrower is a weapon but it can be used for tunnel digging as well.</tip>
    <tip>Use the Molotov Cocktail or Flamethrower to temporary keep hedgehogs from passing terrain such as tunnels or platforms.</tip>
    <tip>Like Hedgewars? Become a fan on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Hedgewars">Facebook</a> or follow us on <a href="https://twitter.com/hedgewars">Twitter</a>.</tip>
    <tip>Feel free to draw your own graves, hats, flags or even maps and themes! But note that you’ll have to share them somewhere to use them online.</tip>
    <tip>Keep your video card drivers up to date to avoid issues playing the game.</tip>
    <tip>Heads or tails? Type “/rnd” in the lobby and you’ll find out. Also “/rnd rock paper scissors” works!</tip>
    <tip>You’re able to associate Hedgewars-related files (savegames and demo recordings) with the game to launch them right from your favorite file or web browser.</tip>
    <tip>Dud mines are not harmless: Although their timer is broken, they can still explode if they took too much abuse!</tip>
    <tip>Love is hot! Use Seduction to thaw frozen hedgehogs.</tip>
    <tip>Smoke coming from a barrel is an indicator that it is low on “health” and even small amounts of damage might cause it to burst.</tip>
    <tip>Barrels start with 60 health and take damage like hedgehogs, so they need some abuse until they explode.</tip>
    <tip>Need more bounce power? Change the bounce strength of grenades, cluster bombs, old limburgers and mines while holding [precise] and pressing one of the timer keys.</tip>
    <tip>Did you forget the goals or game modifiers inside the game? Hit the pause or quit key to review them again!</tip>
    <tip>You can punch, whip and hammer other things than just hedgehogs. Hit them all!</tip>
    <tip>If not mentioned otherwise, mines normally explode after 3 seconds.</tip>
    <tip>In King Mode, your king will start out healthier, stronger and more resistant to damage and blows than the minions.</tip>
    <tip>In King Mode, the king will take damage each turn when there are no minions left in the team.</tip>
    <tip>The whip also hits hedgehogs and objects behind a thin wall.</tip>
    <tip>A cleaver deals more damage the faster it’s moving.</tip>
    <tip>You can drop cakes from cliffs, but you have to stand very close to the edge, so be careful.</tip>
    <tip>Use your rope to push away other hedgehogs, e.g. by sliding on the ground. This technique is known as “rope-knocking”.</tip>
    <tip>Don’t stand still on an icy slope, or you will slip away. Alternatively, you can hold down [precise].</tip>
    <tip>In the lands of Snow and Christmas, the snow piles up over time, unless the land is indestructible.</tip>
    <tip>Be aware in lands of Snow and Christmas, because girders are made of slippery ice.</tip>
    <tip>The retreat time depends on the weapon you used. Be careful, some weapons don’t have a retreat time and immediately end your turn!</tip>
    <tip>With a bit of skill, you can knock hedgehogs by jumping out from under them.</tip>
    <tip>A timed attack with shoryuken, pick hammer or sine gun can cancel fall damage.</tip>
    <tip>Your hedgehog does not collide with projectiles while it is in mid-air.</tip>
    <tip>Holes left by drill rockets, sniper rifles and the Desert Eagle are large enough to fire portals through them—if your aim is precise enough.</tip>
    <tip>Collect a first aid kit to cure your poisoned hedgehog.</tip>
    <tip>You can also collect crates while using RC plane, shoryuken, pick hammer and kamikaze.</tip>
    <tip>Be careful not to blow yourselves up when using a blow torch to approach a crate.</tip>
    <tip>Air mines remain passive within the first 5 seconds of a turn before they start seeking for hedgehogs.</tip>
    <tip>Keep a safe distance from air mines! Once an air mine starts chasing you, it’s hard to escape without utilities.</tip>
    <tip>Air mines explode after a quarter of the time set for regular mines.</tip>
    <tip>When a cleaver in the landscape receives 30 or more damage in a single blow, there’s a chance it falls off. This chance increases with the damage.</tip>
    <tip>Mind the wind, because flames and some projectiles are affected by wind.</tip>
    <tip>Use a blow torch to push hedgehogs and mines with a long timer.</tip>
    <tip>Running with a blow torch into a barrel is an explosive recipe for disaster!</tip>
    <tip>Enter “/help” in chat for a list of chat commands. Chat commands give you access to some special features like taunts or voting.</tip>
    <windows-only>
        <tip>You can find your Hedgewars configuration files under “My Documents\Hedgewars”. Create backups or take the files with you, but don’t edit them by hand.</tip>
    </windows-only>
    <mac-only>
        <tip>You can find your Hedgewars configuration files under “Library/Application Support/Hedgewars” in your home directory. Create backups or take the files with you, but don’t edit them by hand.</tip>
    </mac-only>
    <linux-only>
        <tip>You can find your Hedgewars configuration files under “.hedgewars” in your home directory. Create backups or take the files with you, but don’t edit them by hand.</tip>
    </linux-only>
</tips>
