<!-- This is not xml actually, but it looks and behaves like it.
     Including an xml library would need too much resources.
     Tips between the platform specific tags are shown only on those platforms.
     Do not escape characters or use the CDATA tag. -->
<tips>
    <tip>Airson cluiche ann an cinneadh, cha leig thu leas ach an aon dath a thaghadh 's a thagh caraid. Stiùirichidh sibh na gràineagan agaibh fhèin fa leth fhathast ach caillidh no buannaichidh sibh còmhla.</tip>
    <tip>Tha airm ann nach dèan ach beagan a dhochann ach dh'fhaoidte gum bi iad glè èifeachdach a-rèir an t-suidheachaidh. Feuch gun cleachd thu Iolaire an fhàsaich gus iomadh gràineag a chur dhan mhuir.</tip>
    <tip>Mur eil thu cinnteach na nì thu agus mur eil thu airson connadh a chaitheamh gun fheum, leig seachad do chuairt. Ach na fuirich ro fhada on a thigeadh bàs obann ort!</tip>
    <tip>A bheil thu airson ròpannan a shàbhaladh? Leig às an ròpa fad 's a bhios tu san adhair is loisg e a-rithist. Cho fad 's nach bean thu ri tìr is a chuimsicheas tu gu soirbheachail, cleachdaidh tu an ròpa agad a-rithist gun a bhith a' caitheamh connaidh!</tip>
    <tip>Mur eil thu ag iarraidh gun cleachd daoine eile am far-ainm as fhearr leat air an fhrithealaiche oifigeil, clàraich cunntas air <a href="http://www.hedgewars.org/">http://www.hedgewars.org/</a>.</tip>
    <tip>A bheil thu seachd searbh dhen gheama àbhaisteach? Feuch fear dhe na miseanan — bheir iad dòigh-chluiche eadar-dhealaichte dhut a-rèir an fhir a thagh thu</tip>
    <tip>Clàraichidh sinn an geama mu dheireadh a chluich thu mar demo gu fèin-obrachail. Tagh “Geama ionadail” agus tagh putan nan “Demo” taobh deas aig a' bhonn gus an cluich no an stiùireadh.</tip>
    <tip>'S e bathar-bog saor (Open Source) a th' ann an Hedgewars a tha sinn a' cruthachadh gu saor-thoileach. Ma tha duilgheadas agad, faighnich air a' bhòrd-bhrath no tadhail air an t-seòmar IRC againn!</tip>
    <tip>'S e bathar-bog saor (Open Source) a th' ann an Hedgewars a tha sinn a' cruthachadh gu saor-thoileach. Ma tha e a' còrdadh riut, nach doir thu tabhartas airgid no obrach dhuinn?</tip>
    <tip>'S e bathar-bog saor (Open Source) a th' ann an Hedgewars a tha sinn a' cruthachadh gu saor-thoileach. Co-roinn e le do theaghlach is caraidean mar a thogras tu!</tip>
    <tip>'S e bathar-bog saor (Open Source) a th' ann an Hedgewars a tha sinn a' cruthachadh gu saor-thoileach a cum tlachd! Coinnich ris an luchd-leasachaidh ann an <a href="irc://irc.freenode.net/hedgewars">#hedgewars</a>!</tip>
    <tip>Bi fèill-chluiche oifigeil againn o àm gu àm. Sgaoilidh sinn brathan-naidheachd mu na tachartasan air <a href="http://www.hedgewars.org/">http://www.hedgewars.org/</a> beagan làithean ro làimh.</tip>
    <tip>Tha Hedgewars ri fhaighinn ann an iomadh cànan. Ma tha an cànan agad a dhìth no an t-eadar-theangachadh ro shean, nach cuir thu fios thugainn?</tip>
    <tip>Gabhaidh Hedgewars a ruith air iomadh siostam-obrachaidh, a' gabhail a-steach Microsoft Windows, Mac OS X agus GNU/Linux.</tip>
    <tip>Cuimhnich gur urrainn dhut na geamannan agad fhèin a suidheachadh air an lìonra ionadail no air loidhne. Tha barrachd roghainnean na geama simplidh agad.</tip>
    <tip>Ma tha iomadh pada-geama agad, ceangail iad ris mus tòisich thu an geama agus sònraich an stiùireadh dha na sgiobannan agad.</tip>
    <tip>Bu chòir dhut beagan fois a ghabhail on chluich gach uair a thìde air eagal 's gun cuir e an sgithear ort.</tip>
    <tip>Mur eil comas luathachaidh bathair-chruaidh OpenGL aig a' chairt-ghrafaigeachd agad, feuch an cuir thu an comas modh na càileachd ìseil gus piseach a thoirt air an dèanadas.</tip>
    <tip>Mur eil comas luathachaidh bathair-chruaidh OpenGL aig a' chairt-ghrafaigeachd agad, feuch gu ùraich thu na draibhearan aice.</tip>
    <tip>Cuiridh sinn fàilte air molaidhean is beachdan cuideachail. Ma tha rud ann nach eil a' còrdadh riut no ma tha deagh bheachd agad, innis dhuinn mu dhèidhinn!</tip>
    <tip>For your own benefit we'd like you to be polite and friendly while playing on our server. Also please keep in mind that some players are minors!</tip>
    <tip>Special game modes such as “Vampirism” or “Karma” allow you to develop completely new tactics. Try them in a custom game!</tip>
    <tip>Please don't install Hedgewars on computers you don’t own (school, university, work, etc.) unless you got permission. We don't want you to get into any trouble.</tip>
    <tip>Hedgewars can be perfect for short games during breaks. Just ensure you don’t add too many hedgehogs or use an huge map. Reducing time and health might help as well.</tip>
    <tip>No hedgehogs were harmed in making this game.</tip>
    <tip>There are three different jumps available. Tap [high jump] twice to do a very high/backwards jump.</tip>
    <tip>Afraid of falling off a cliff? Hold down [precise] to turn [left] or [right] without actually moving.</tip>
    <tip>Some weapons require special strategies or just lots of training, so don’t give up on a particular tool if you miss an enemy once.</tip>
    <tip>Most weapons won’t work once they touch the water. The Homing Bee as well as the Cake are exceptions to this.</tip>
    <tip>The Old Limburger only causes a small explosion. However the wind affected smelly cloud can poison lots of hogs at once.</tip>
    <tip>The Piano Strike is the most damaging air strike. You’ll lose the hedgehog performing it, so there’s a huge downside as well.</tip>
    <tip>The Homing Bee can be tricky to use. Its turn radius depends on its velocity, so try to not use full power.</tip>
    <tip>Sticky Mines are a perfect tool to create small chain reactions knocking enemy hedgehogs into dire situations … or water.</tip>
    <tip>The Hammer is most effective when used on bridges or girders. Hit hogs will just break through the ground.</tip>
    <tip>If you’re stuck behind an enemy hedgehog, use the Hammer to free yourself without getting damaged by an explosion.</tip>
    <tip>The Cake’s maximum walking distance depends on the ground it has to pass. Use [attack] to detonate it early.</tip>
    <tip>The Flame Thrower is a weapon but it can be used for tunnel digging as well.</tip>
    <tip>Use the Molotov or Flame Thrower to temporary keep hedgehogs from passing terrain such as tunnels or platforms.</tip>
    <tip>Want to know who’s behind the game? Click on the Hedgewars logo in the main menu to see the credits.</tip>
    <tip>Like Hedgewars? Become a fan on <a href="http://www.facebook.com/Hedgewars">Facebook</a> or follow us on <a href="http://twitter.com/hedgewars">Twitter</a></tip>
    <tip>Feel free to draw your own graves, hats, flags or even maps and themes! But note that you’ll have to share them somewhere to use them online.</tip>
    <tip>Keep your video card drivers up to date to avoid issues playing the game.</tip>
    <tip>Heads or tails? Type “/rnd” in the lobby and you’ll find out. Also “/rnd rock paper scissors” works!</tip>
    <tip>You’re able to associate Hedgewars related files (savegames and demo recordings) with the game to launch them right from your favorite file or web browser.</tip>
    <tip>Dud mines are not harmless: Although their timer is broken, they can still explode if they took too much abuse!</tip>
    <tip>Love is hot! Use Seduction to thaw frozen hedgehogs.</tip>
    <tip>Smoke coming from a barrel is an indicator that it is low on “health” and even small amounts of damage might cause it to burst.</tip>
    <tip>Barrels start with 60 health and take damage like hedgehogs, so they need some abuse until they explode.</tip>
    <tip>Need more bounce power? Change the bounce strength of grenades, cluster bombs, old limburgers and mines while holding [precise] and pressing one of the timer keys.</tip>
    <tip>Did you forget the goals or game modifiers inside the game? Hit the pause or quit key to review them again!</tip>
    <tip>You can punch, whip and hammer other things than just hedgehogs. Hit them all!</tip>
    <tip>If not mentioned otherwise, mines normally explode after 3 seconds.</tip>
    <tip>In King Mode, your king will start out healthier, stronger and more resistant to damage and blows than the minions.</tip>
    <tip>In King Mode, the king will take damage each turn when there are no minions left in the team.</tip>
    <tip>The whip also hits hedgehogs and objects behind a thin wall.</tip>
    <tip>A cleaver deals more damage the faster it’s moving.</tip>
    <tip>You can drop cakes from cliffs, but you have to stand very close to the edge, so be careful.</tip>
    <tip>Use your rope to push away other hedgehogs i.e. by sliding on the ground. This technique is known as “rope-knocking”.</tip>
    <tip>Don’t stand still on an icy slope, or you will slip away. Alternatively, you can hold down [precise].</tip>
    <tip>In the lands of Snow and Christmas, the snow piles up over time, unless the land is indestructible.</tip>
    <tip>Be aware in lands of Snow and Christmas, because girders are made of slippery ice.</tip>
    <tip>The retreat time depends on the weapon you used. Be careful, some weapons don’t have a retreat time and immediately end your turn!</tip>
    <windows-only>
        <tip>This version of Hedgewars supports <a href="http://www.xfire.com">Xfire</a>. Make sure to add Hedgewars to its game list so your friends can see you playing.</tip>
        <tip>You can find your Hedgewars configuration files under “My Documents\Hedgewars”. Create backups or take the files with you, but don’t edit them by hand.</tip>
    </windows-only>
    <mac-only>
        <tip>You can find your Hedgewars configuration files under “Library/Application Support/Hedgewars” in your home directory. Create backups or take the files with you, but don’t edit them by hand.</tip>
    </mac-only>
    <linux-only>
        <tip>You can find your Hedgewars configuration files under “.hedgewars” in your home directory. Create backups or take the files with you, but don’t edit them by hand.</tip>
    </linux-only>
</tips>